<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY GFDL  SYSTEM "fdl-appendix.xml">
  <!ENTITY app "Sound Juicer">
  <!ENTITY appversion "0.4.2">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "2.0">

  <!ENTITY mike "Mike Hearn">
  <!ENTITY mike-addr "mike@theoretic.com">
]>
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Template Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project:
	  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
-->


<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 0.0.1
  Last modified: March 23, 2002
  Maintainers:
               Laszlo Kovacs  <laszlo.kovacs@sun.com>
               Dan Mueth      <muet@alumni.uchicago.edu>
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->



<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="en">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>&app; Manual</title>
    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>
      <holder>&mike; (&mike-addr;)</holder>
    </copyright>

  <!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2000</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

  -->
  
<!-- An address can be added to the publisher information.  If a role is
     not specified, the publisher/author is the same for all versions of the
     document.  -->
    <publisher>
      <publishername> GNOME Documentation Project </publishername>
    </publisher>

   &legal;
   <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change
        any of this. -->

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Mike</firstname>
        <surname>Hearn</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <address> <email>&mike-addr;</email> </address>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
<!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
      maintainers,  etc. Commented out by default.
       <othercredit role="translator">
        <firstname>Latin</firstname>
        <surname>Translator 1</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname>
          <address> <email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address>
        </affiliation>
        <contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
      </othercredit>
-->
    </authorgroup>

<!-- According to GNU FDL, revision history is mandatory if you are -->
<!-- modifying/reusing someone else's document.  If not, you can omit it. -->
<!-- Remember to remove the &manrevision; entity from the revision entries other
-->
<!-- than the current revision. -->
<!-- The revision numbering system for GNOME manuals is as follows: -->
<!-- * the revision number consists of two components -->
<!-- * the first component of the revision number reflects the release version of the GNOME desktop. -->
<!-- * the second component of the revision number is a decimal unit that is incremented with each revision of the manual. -->
<!-- For example, if the GNOME desktop release is V2.x, the first version of the manual that -->
<!-- is written in that desktop timeframe is V2.0, the second version of the manual is V2.1, etc. -->
<!-- When the desktop release version changes to V3.x, the revision number of the manual changes -->
<!-- to V3.0, and so on. -->

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>&app; Manual V&manrevision;</revnumber>
        <date>6th July 2003</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para role="author">&mike;
            <email>&mike-addr;</email>
          </para>
          <para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

<!-- Translators may also add here feedback address for translations -->
  </articleinfo>

 <!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->
 <!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
 <sect1 id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect2 id="aboutex">
   <title>About &app;</title>
   <indexterm>
     <primary>Sound Juicer</primary>
     <secondary>Manual</secondary>
     <tertiary>sound-juicer</tertiary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>
     &app; is a simple and clean CD ripper tool. It allows you to
     extract the audio from audio compact discs and convert them into
     a variety of audio formats your computer can understand and play.
   </para>
   <para>
     It has several useful features, for instance it can look up the
     titles and artists of the tracks on your CD from the internet,
     using the freely available MusicBrainz service.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="notice">
   <title>Notice</title>
   <para>
     &app; is currently in development, so this manual may not
     reflect the program as you see it. If it doesn't, please file a
     bug in Gnome bugzilla against sound-juicer, or email &mike-addr;
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 id="using">
   <title>Using &app;</title>
   <para>
     When you start &app;, it will examine the CD in the currently selected
     drive, and try and locate information about its contents. It can
     match against things like the serial number, but also the length
     and positions of the tracks - this means that sometimes you may
     get a false hit, and the details will be filled out
     incorrectly. Don't worry though, they are easy to change.
   </para>

   <para>
     This is what &app; typically looks like when first started:
   </para>

   <figure>
     <title>&app; on startup</title>
     <screenshot>
       <mediaobject>
	 <imageobject>
           <imagedata fileref="figures/startup" format="PNG"/>
	 </imageobject>
	 <textobject>
           <phrase>&app; at startup</phrase>
	 </textobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </screenshot>
   </figure>

   <para>
     At the top of the window there are a couple of entry boxes for
     the disc artist and title. You should fill this out appropriately
     for the disc currently in the drive. For instance, if the disc is
     an album, put the artist and the name of the album in these
     entry boxes. For a single, the name of the artist and the track
     will do (as you can see in the above screenshot). If the disc
     is by multiple artists, you can just put "Various" or leave it blank.
   </para>

   <para>
     That information is placed in the resultant files so they can be
     easily catalogued and searched by music playing software later,
     so it's a good idea to try and fill it out accurately - it will
     make finding and sorting them much easier.
   </para>

   <para>
     Each track <emphasis>also</emphasis> has a title and artist
     field, which should be set appropriately. Again, this
     information will be encoded into the output files. You don't
     have to extract every track on the CD, if you'd like to exclude
     some, uncheck the box in the "Extract?" column. You can toggle
     the status of all the tracks at once by using the Edit menu.
   </para>
   
   <tip>
     <para>
       When you edit the disc artist field (at the top), all the
       track artist fields are updated to reflect that. This saves
       you a lot of typing - as most discs are by a single artist, it
       means you only have to enter it once for the artist field to
       be updated everywhere.
     </para>
   </tip>

   <para>
     The <guilabel>Duration</guilabel> field shows you the total
     length of the CD in the current drive.
   </para>

   <para>
     The <guibutton>Re-read</guibutton> button is useful for when you
     change CDs but don't want to restart the program - pressing it
     will cause &app; to update its list of tracks.
   </para>

   <para>
     When things are set up to your liking, press
     the <guibutton>Extract</guibutton> button, and &app; will begin
     reading the audio from the CD and saving it to disk. By default,
     this is the "~/Music" directory in your home directory, but you
     can change it in the <interface>Preferences window</interface>.
   </para>

   <warning>
     <para>
       Extracting a CD can take a <emphasis>long time</emphasis>,
       depending on the speed of your computer. By default &app;
       compresses the audio at the same time as extracting it from
       the CD so it takes less space on disk, however this is a time
       consuming process. You don't have to sit and watch it though,
       just minimize it, or move it to a different virtual desktop.
     </para>
   </warning>
   
 </sect1>


 <sect1 id="preferences">
   <title>Preferences</title>
   <para>
     The preferences window allows you to control:
   </para>
   
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para> Which CD drive &app; uses if you have more than one</para></listitem>
     
     <listitem><para> Where the extracted audio is placed on disk</para></listitem>
     
     <listitem><para> Which file format/codec is used for the extracted audio</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <figure>
     <title>Preferences window</title>
     <screenshot>
       <mediaobject>
	 <imageobject>
           <imagedata fileref="figures/prefs" format="PNG"/>
	 </imageobject>
	 <textobject>
           <phrase>Preferences window</phrase>
	 </textobject>
       </mediaobject>
     </screenshot>
   </figure>
   
   <para>
     If you have multiple CD drives in your system, there is a drop
     down list at the top which lets you choose the one to use by
     default. You can also browse for a directory to place the audio
     files in.
   </para>

   <para>
     The <guilabel>Output Name</guilabel> section lets you control how
     the audio files are layed out in your chosen directory. For
     instance, in the default setup, the first track of my CD might be
     extracted to "~/Music/iio/Rapture/01 - Rapture [Radio
     Edit].ogg".
   </para>

   <para>
     The <guibutton>Strip special characters</guibutton> checkbox
     controls whether the file name should be made safe for the
     command line. That involves removing characters like /, \, *, ?
     and so on. It's probably a good idea to have this checked.
   </para>

   
   <sect2>
     <title>Output format</title>

     <para>
       Here you can choose which file format you want to save your
       files to. The default is
       <ulink type="http" url="http://www.vorbis.org/">Ogg
	 Vorbis</ulink>, which is recommended due to its high in
	 quality, low in size nature, as well as being an open format
	 available to all. Ogg Vorbis can be played by virtually all
	 Linux installations out of the box, and
       <ulink type="http" 
       url="http://www.nullsoft.com/">WinAmp</ulink>
       for Windows also supports it.
     </para>

     <para>
       Other formats are available however. The MP3 codec is widely
       known and used, and has good hardware support. If you have a
       portable MP3 player that doesn't accept Vorbis files, you may
       wish to use this so you can upload it to the device.
     </para>

     <para>
       FLAC is a lossless codec, as opposed to Vorbis and MP3 which
       are lossy. Lossless codecs don't throw any information away at
       all, which means you get a 100% faithful reproduction of the
       original sound. Lossy codecs use complex mathematical
       constructions, called psychoacoustic models, to eliminate
       information that you cannot normally hear. The end result
       sounds virtually identical to the original, even though it is
       in reality substantially different.
     </para>

     <para>
       If quality is of the highest concern to you, and you have lots
       of disk space to burn, you might want to try FLAC. The WAV raw
       audio format is the lowest common denominator format - it
       isn't compressed at all, and will give the biggest files. It's
       often useful for professional audio work, but for most uses
       you won't want to choose this option.
     </para>

     <para>
       Some of the options may be unavailable here. If that's the
       case, you need to install support for the relevant formats
       into GStreamer. The exact way you do this will depend on your setup.
     </para>
   </sect2>
 </sect1>
   
 
&GFDL;

</article>


